<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>To The Trains</title>
    <link href="https://tothetrains.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://tothetrains.uk" />
    <updated>2023-07-31T20:27:11+01:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Seb J.</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://tothetrains.uk</id>

    <entry>
        <title>The Elizabeth Line, London, and Crossrail in 2023</title>
        <author>
            <name>Seb J.</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tothetrains.uk/london-elizabeth-line-crossrail-2023/"/>
        <id>https://tothetrains.uk/london-elizabeth-line-crossrail-2023/</id>

        <updated>2023-07-31T20:26:07+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/vlcsnap-2023-03-26-12h38m37s327.jpeg" alt="The front of a Class 345 Elizabeth line train as it pulls into Custom House in the core section." />
                    <p>The Elizabeth line - over a decade in the making and a sizable addition to Transport for London's portfolio of railway and metro services. The core section of the line opened for revenue earning service on 24 May 2022, however Crossrail (as the project is officially called) has sort of been in operation for much longer than that. Let's delve into the journey of the Elizabeth line, shall we?</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/vlcsnap-2023-03-26-12h38m37s327.jpeg" alt="The front of a Class 345 Elizabeth line train as it pulls into Custom House in the core section." />
                <p>The Elizabeth line - over a decade in the making and a sizable addition to Transport for London's portfolio of railway and metro services. The core section of the line opened for revenue earning service on 24 May 2022, however Crossrail (as the project is officially called) has sort of been in operation for much longer than that. Let's delve into the journey of the Elizabeth line, shall we?</p>

<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/SM5GxvypePo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<hr>
<p>Over the last year the line has been opening in sections, starting with the core section, followed by the opening of Bond Street, and then the introduction of through-running services. However, the Elizabeth line has been in service for much longer than that, albeit operating under the "TfL Rail" brand. This was the case from May 2015, when MTR took control of the metro service between London Liverpool and Shenfield - now the eastern branch of the line.</p>
<p>The eastern branch was populated by Class 345s from June 2017, before the units then rolled out on the western branch by July 2020. With the launch of the core section, these branches took on the Elizabeth line name and branding, including station signage and on the units themselves. Numerous stations were upgraded to ensure step-free access from the platform to the street. This means there are plenty of lifts across the network, including some that even travel diagonally.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/PXL_20220603_155459704.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/responsive/PXL_20220603_155459704-xs.jpg 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/responsive/PXL_20220603_155459704-sm.jpg 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/responsive/PXL_20220603_155459704-md.jpg 768w"  alt="A Class 345 at London Liverpool Street donning the Elizabeth line branding." width="4032" height="3024">
<figcaption >A Class 345 at London Liverpool Street donning the Elizabeth line branding.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Between Paddington and Abbey Wood is a plethora of exceptional architecture, with each station's design subtly inspired by its local area. The Elizabeth Line's futuristic character is prominent in the extensive tunnels and spacious walkways and platforms. IU recommend taking a look at some of the "Design &amp; Architecture" videos published by the Crossrail Project for more insight. There's no doubt that the top priority for the Elizabeth line was capacity; we can see this reflected in the rolling stock, too.</p>
<p>The Class 345s have nine cars per unit and stretch over 200 metres in length. The platforms are exceptionally long to accommodate this - if you've got somewhere you need to get to quickly, it really does matter what end of the train you board. These trains are effectively built for the National Rail network and yet are being operated as a metro service. When I visited in 2020, there was a dense timetable in operation with trains arriving every five minutes. These are now even more frequent.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/DJI_20220603_102826_22_pano.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/responsive/DJI_20220603_102826_22_pano-xs.jpg 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/responsive/DJI_20220603_102826_22_pano-sm.jpg 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/responsive/DJI_20220603_102826_22_pano-md.jpg 768w"  alt="A wide angle view of the interior of the Class 345s." width="2190" height="1732">
<figcaption >A wide angle view of the interior of the Class 345s.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>On board is what we've come to except from new commuter trains in the UK: air conditioning; digital passenger information screens; transverse and longitudinal seating; four designated wheelchair and accessible areas. At each station and above the platform edge doors are more digital displays with information about the train service. I do appreciate having the screen doors on a busy railway network.</p>
<p>There's a lot to like about the Elizabeth line, but what stood out to me when I rode the line for the first time last year was its speed. It's quick, and the Class 345's acceleration is impressive. It feels even more noticeable when you're underground and in the tunnels of the Elizabeth line.</p>
<ul>
<li>30 minutes from Abbey Wood to Paddington.</li>
<li>35 minutes from Heathrow to Paddington.</li>
<li>Considerably cheaper than the Heathrow Express (£12.70, as of writing).</li>
</ul>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/DJI_20220603_114105_75.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/responsive/DJI_20220603_114105_75-xs.jpg 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/responsive/DJI_20220603_114105_75-sm.jpg 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/13/responsive/DJI_20220603_114105_75-md.jpg 768w"  alt="Screen doors line the edge of the platform, which connects to a wide and spacious walkway." width="4032" height="3024">
<figcaption >The wide and spacious walkways and platforms maximise capacity beneath the surface.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The full timetable, which marks Crossrail's final major milestone, has been in operation since May of this year, therefore concluding the Elizabeth line journey. And it's been a long journey, not the smoothest process, and one that saw no shortage of setbacks and delays. That's typical for the railways, mind you. But, by the end of it all, London has a fantastic east-to-west railway fit for the commuters of the capital.</p>
<p><em>Sources can be found in the description of the YouTube video.</em></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Obelisk</title>
        <author>
            <name>Seb J.</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tothetrains.uk/obelisk/"/>
        <id>https://tothetrains.uk/obelisk/</id>

        <updated>2022-07-04T18:13:13+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Obelisk is planned to be the main bot for the To The Trains Discord server. Features from Dyno and Statbot will be adopted over time, eventually resulting in the phase out of these additional bots. Obelisk will serve as the main platform for server moderation, engagement, and oversight. During&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><strong>Obelisk</strong> is planned to be the main bot for the To The Trains Discord server. Features from <em>Dyno </em>and <em>Statbot </em>will be adopted over time, eventually resulting in the phase out of these additional bots. Obelisk will serve as the main platform for server moderation, engagement, and oversight. During development the source code will be proprietary - an open source release is tabled for when the majority of planned features are in working order.</p>
<p>Obelisk is programmed in Python with the use of py-cord and dislash.py.</p>
<h2>Help</h2>
<table style="border-collapse: collapse; width: 100%; height: 203px;" border="1">
<tbody>
<tr style="height: 50px;">
<td style="width: 21.4783%; height: 50px;"><strong>Command</strong></td>
<td style="width: 29.5677%; height: 50px;"><strong>Arguments</strong></td>
<td style="width: 48.9539%; height: 50px;"><strong>Description</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 51px;">
<td style="width: 21.4783%; height: 51px;"><code>/ping</code></td>
<td style="width: 29.5677%; height: 51px;"> </td>
<td style="width: 48.9539%; height: 51px;">Identifies and returns bot latency</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 51px;">
<td style="width: 21.4783%; height: 51px;"><code>/version</code></td>
<td style="width: 29.5677%; height: 51px;"> </td>
<td style="width: 48.9539%; height: 51px;">Identifies and returns bot version</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 51px;">
<td style="width: 21.4783%; height: 51px;"><span style="color: #000000;"><code>/suggest</code></span></td>
<td style="width: 29.5677%; height: 51px;"> </td>
<td style="width: 48.9539%; height: 51px;">Opens the "Make a Suggestion" modal</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><code><span style="color: #000000;">(</span>*<span style="color: #000000;">: required)</span></code></span></p>
<h2>Your Data</h2>
<p>Obelisk can react to when a user joins or leaves and fetch the entire server member list, utilising the 'members' intent therefor. Obelisk cannot read the content of messages and can only interpret commands and their respective arguments.</p>
<p>Obelisk collects and stores a database of various statistics:</p>
<ul>
<li>Quantity of messages sent per user</li>
<li>Quantity of users invited per user</li>
<li>Quantity of reactions per user</li>
<li>Quantity of achievements unlocked per user</li>
<li>Duration of server membership per user</li>
<li>If you are boosting/have boosted the server</li>
</ul>
<h2>Formal Inquiries</h2>
<p>For any reason, please contact <a href="mailto:obelisk@tothetrains.uk" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">obelisk@tothetrains.uk</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The EMR Class 158 &quot;Express Sprinter&quot;</title>
        <author>
            <name>Seb J.</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tothetrains.uk/emr-class-158-express-sprinter-overview/"/>
        <id>https://tothetrains.uk/emr-class-158-express-sprinter-overview/</id>

        <updated>2023-07-31T18:04:15+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/158.jpeg" alt="A Class 158 Express Sprinter in an EMR Regional livery standing in Grantham working a service to Norwich." />
                    <figure></figure>
<figure><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Class 158 is a feat of engineering. Constructed during the era of British Rail, it continued to operate throughout the privatisation of the railways and still serves passengers up and down the country today.</span></figure>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/158.jpeg" alt="A Class 158 Express Sprinter in an EMR Regional livery standing in Grantham working a service to Norwich." />
                <figure></figure>
<figure><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Class 158 is a feat of engineering. Constructed during the era of British Rail, it continued to operate throughout the privatisation of the railways and still serves passengers up and down the country today.</span></figure>

<figure>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yNmB9iz5wIk" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
</figure>
<hr>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Known otherwise as the </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Express Sprinter</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, the Class 158 was built by British Rail Engineering Limited from 1989 to 1992. They were brought in as part of a plan to replace British Rail’s ageing first-generation diesel multiple units. They have certainly stood the test of time and are still being operated by a healthy number of TOCs today.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/DJI_20210425_144845_436.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/DJI_20210425_144845_436-xs.jpg 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/DJI_20210425_144845_436-sm.jpg 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/DJI_20210425_144845_436-md.jpg 768w"  alt="An EMR Class 158 Express Sprinter at Peterborough" width="4032" height="3024">
<figcaption >An EMR Class 158 Express Sprinter at Peterborough</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The footage in the video is from a service to Norwich from Liverpool Lime Street, operated by East Midlands Railway. This service in particular is a testament to the Class 158’s passenger-hauling power, with the full trip taking just over five and a half hours and stopping at fifteen intermediary stations along the way.  The </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sprinter </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">family of trains were constructed to cover all sorts of routes across the country.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The majority of the </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Express Sprinter </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">fleet still in service today is formed of 2-car units, though some TOCs, such as GWR, do operate a handful of 3-car units for added capacity. The trains have a maximum speed of 90 miles per hour, and can accelerate at a maximum of 0.8 metres per second squared.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/Seating-2.png" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/Seating-2-xs.png 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/Seating-2-sm.png 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/Seating-2-md.png 768w"  alt="The 2+2 seating arrangement on board a Class 158 Express Sprinter service" width="1920" height="1080">
<figcaption >The 2+2 seating arrangement on board an EMR Class 158</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Now, let’s take a look at what this DMU has to offer on board. Immediately at the ends of each carriage is a luggage rack to fit a few larger items that won’t fit in the overhead luggage racks or beneath your seat. Capacity is maximised with a 2+2 seating arrangement with a mix of airline-style and table seats. That leaves a particularly narrow walkway down the train.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are bins throughout the train and space for two bicycles on board, too. A toilet and accessible area can be found; a wheelchair ramp will be required to board the train, though. Level boarding tends to be more of a newer consideration in rolling stock design. Dotted throughout the carriage are digital PIS displays with general journey information. The text is particularly high-contrast with the yellow font on a blue background.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/At-Speed-2.png" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/At-Speed-2-xs.png 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/At-Speed-2-sm.png 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/At-Speed-2-md.png 768w"  alt="A Class 158 at speed on a service to Norwich from Liverpool Lime Street" width="1920" height="1080">
<figcaption >The interior of an EMR Class 158 - there is a mix of airline-style and table seating</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are a couple priority seats allocated on the train for those who need them, which is always a good thing. All seats have pull-down armrests and the airline-style seats have seatback tables with enough space for a few items.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Keep in mind, though, that these units will have seen various refurbishments from different TOCs over the years. So, with that said, you’re likely to see a variety of interiors depending on where you are in the country.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Watch the London Underground live with TrainTrackr&#x27;s 333 LED display</title>
        <author>
            <name>Seb J.</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tothetrains.uk/watch-the-london-underground-live-with-traintrackrs-333-led-display/"/>
        <id>https://tothetrains.uk/watch-the-london-underground-live-with-traintrackrs-333-led-display/</id>

        <updated>2022-06-02T17:14:38+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/tfl3_4.jpg" alt="Photo of board LEDs illuminating" />
                    <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">TrainTrackr’s London Underground live tracker is no doubt the perfect product for any rail and transport enthusiast. The premise is simple; the board connects to your home Wi-Fi to display train arrival data from London’s vast tube network. And it does so in real-time by harnessing Transport for London’s live APIs to automatically update 333 LEDs.</span></p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/tfl3_4.jpg" alt="Photo of board LEDs illuminating" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">TrainTrackr’s London Underground live tracker is no doubt the perfect product for any rail and transport enthusiast. The premise is simple; the board connects to your home Wi-Fi to display train arrival data from London’s vast tube network. And it does so in real-time by harnessing Transport for London’s live APIs to automatically update 333 LEDs.</span></p>
<hr>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Pictured below is the large variant. Its dimensions are 40 cm x 30 cm, taking up quite a bit of room to pack in all those LEDs. Thankfully, in the box are also some wooden supports that can be used to prop up the tracker with minimal effort. Also included in the box is a USB power cable, a neat TrainTrackr logo sticker, and the setup instructions.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/PXL_20220218_154023799.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/PXL_20220218_154023799-xs.jpg 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/PXL_20220218_154023799-sm.jpg 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/PXL_20220218_154023799-md.jpg 768w"  alt="Full view of the tracker, with LEDs illuminated to indicate train arrivals" width="4032" height="3024"></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Enabling your tracker should be a straightforward process, though I encountered a technical mishap while trying to connect mine to my Wi-Fi network. TrainTrackr foresaw this, however, and I was able to follow their supplied alternative procedure, connecting directly to the board and configuring the network from there.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After setting up a Wi-Fi connection the tracker just works, it’s particularly amusing to watch all the LEDs begin to flash with activity. There is an LED for each tube station and, upon the arrival of a train will illuminate in the colour of the service’s respective line. </span></p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--left"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/PXL_20220218_154213201-2.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/PXL_20220218_154213201-2-xs.jpg 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/PXL_20220218_154213201-2-sm.jpg 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/PXL_20220218_154213201-2-md.jpg 768w"  alt="Close-up image of the 'London TrainTrackr' logo." width="4032" height="3024"></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This works incredibly well for the majority of lines, though you might have realised that it’s a tad difficult to represent the colours of the Bakerloo and Northern lines, for example, on a simple LED module. TrainTrackr opted for alternative colours to represent these lines, with the former using a bright orange hue instead, in this instance. The impact of this is minimal once you’ve adjusted to the changes.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The tracker can also be connected to the TrainTrackr website with a unique code, too. They offer an online portal where you can check in on the status of your board and adjust the brightness of the LED modules. There is also the option to enable a ‘night mode’ which reduces the brightness of or turns off the LEDs entirely. I particularly enjoy this functionality - otherwise, this London Underground tracker might as well be a floodlight with its activity in the evening.</span></p>
<hr>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/PXL_20220218_154034214.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/PXL_20220218_154034214-xs.jpg 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/PXL_20220218_154034214-sm.jpg 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/PXL_20220218_154034214-md.jpg 768w"  alt="Close up of the microcontroller powering the board." width="4032" height="3024"></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Also promoted on the product page is how maker-friendly the product is. For enthusiasts with programming and microcontroller expertise, TrainTrackr has </span><a href="https://blog.traintrackr.io/?p=27"><span style="font-weight: 400;">an article detailing the steps to reprogram your board</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Those interested in the Arduino platform might have spotted the ESP8266 module, and yes, with the right libraries and board installed, you can indeed use the Arduino IDE to upload your own code.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">TrainTrackr will, in future, support custom API integrations so that you can send your own data directly to your tracker without the need to flash it with new software.</span></p>
<hr>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Are you a frequent user of the District, Central, or Northern line? Well, you can find also boards for these lines featuring LEDs for both directions. Also available on the TrainTrackr <a href="https://www.traintrackr.co.uk/product">products page</a> is the smaller variant of the London Underground tracker, and a variety of other rapid transit and country/state maps.</span></p>
<p><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Happy tracking!</span></em></p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--wide"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/PXL_20220218_154232210-4.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/PXL_20220218_154232210-4-xs.jpg 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/PXL_20220218_154232210-4-sm.jpg 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/PXL_20220218_154232210-4-md.jpg 768w"  alt="Close-up of the LEDs illuminated in the colour of the respective arrival's line." width="4032" height="3024"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>About</title>
        <author>
            <name>Seb J.</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tothetrains.uk/about/"/>
        <id>https://tothetrains.uk/about/</id>
            <category term="Info"/>

        <updated>2022-01-28T22:15:19+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    To The Trains started with Seb on the 31st of July, 2020. The original goal was simple: to document Britain's railways. And it's been much the same ever since, though plenty has happened in the meantime. First introduced as a YouTube channel, To The Trains&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>To The Trains started with Seb on the 31st of July, 2020. The original goal was simple: to document Britain's railways. And it's been much the same ever since, though plenty has happened in the meantime.</p>
<p>First introduced as a YouTube channel, To The Trains served and continues to serve as your destination for comprehensive videos on everything from rolling stock to routes. With the occasional livestream, too, the channel is home to over 20 videos amassing in excess of 40,000 views and 600 subscribers. Videos are produced by a team of one; it was started by a rail enthusiast for rail enthusiasts.</p>
<p>Just over a year following the channel's first upload saw the introduction of Railway Rover, the podcast from To The Trains for everyone with a special interest in trains and the railway. Offering a more laid-back conversational approach and a longer format, Railway Rover was designed to supplement content on the channel, while serving as a gateway to listeners on other platforms, too.</p>
<p>And now we've just arrived at our next destination. Please alight here for longer-form articles and blog posts from To The Trains, exclusively on <em>tothetrains.uk</em>. You'll find all sorts of additional written content, from trip reports and railway product reviews to the latest news from across the transport industry. This is yet another outlet for To The Trains posts and media, and we're happy to have you here.</p>
<p>We hope that you'll get involved - whether that be keeping up-to-date with the latest posts, joining the conversation on our socials, or even <a href="https://tothetrains.uk/write-with-us/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">writing with us</a>.</p>
<p>Thank you for sticking around. Where next?</p>
<p><strong>To The Trains, 2022</strong></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Write with us</title>
        <author>
            <name>Seb J.</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tothetrains.uk/write-with-us/"/>
        <id>https://tothetrains.uk/write-with-us/</id>
            <category term="Info"/>

        <updated>2022-01-28T21:56:26+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    If you're a rail enthusiast looking to volunteer your knowledge and share your expertise, join the team and write for us. As a writer, you'll be helping us work towards our collective goal to document Britain's railways (and beyond!) by piecing together articles on the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>If you're a rail enthusiast looking to volunteer your knowledge and share your expertise, join the team and write for us. As a writer, you'll be helping us work towards our collective goal to document Britain's railways (and beyond!) by piecing together articles on the topics you're interested in. And if a railway-themed podcast peaks your interest, too, you'll be able to contribute to Railway Rover with research, planning, and appearances.</p>
<p>This is a role with minimal obligations, <em>tothetrains.uk</em> is all about sharing the news and experiences relevant to us. That means you can write as much or as little as works best for you. You might be a prolific writer with a special interest in transport, or an enthusiast who wants to make themselves heard. We'd like to hear from you!</p>
<p>We're looking for any of the following, but this isn't an exhaustive list and we're open to all pitches:</p>
<ul>
<li>Latest industry news (last 48 hours)</li>
<li>Industry analysis (developments from the last week/month)</li>
<li>Rolling stock overviews (opinion/factual)</li>
<li>Trip reports (opinion)</li>
<li>Railway product reviews (opinion)</li>
<li>The state of the railways (opinion)</li>
</ul>
<p>So, if you're interested, let's talk. Send an email to <a href="mailto:seb@tothetrains.uk">seb@tothetrains.uk</a> or join our Discord server to find out more about hopping on board.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Railway Rover: Western Europe&#x27;s Railways</title>
        <author>
            <name>Seb J.</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tothetrains.uk/railway-rover-western-europes-railways/"/>
        <id>https://tothetrains.uk/railway-rover-western-europes-railways/</id>
            <category term="Railway Rover"/>

        <updated>2022-01-30T20:58:52+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Welcome back to Railway Rover - this episode now approaching takes a look at continental Europe’s railways, particularly in western Europe. We’re joined by Ambroise, a resident of Belgium, to introduce you to the railways across the (English) Channel and highlight some key comparisons. We&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Welcome back to <a href="https://tothetrains.uk/tags/railway-rover-podcast/">Railway Rover</a> - this episode now approaching takes a look at continental Europe’s railways, particularly in western Europe. We’re joined by Ambroise, a resident of Belgium, to introduce you to the railways across the (English) Channel and highlight some key comparisons. We discuss everything from the train operating companies themselves to the rolling stock and those double decker trains unheard of in the UK. This is a particularly insightful episode for anything interested in the railways across Europe.</span></p>
<h4>Watch on YouTube</h4>
<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/UXkm4akpZS8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<h4>Railway Rover</h4>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Railway Rover is your all line rover ticket to the latest in the rail industry. It's a podcast covering everything from rolling stock to routes, laid-back and conversational by design, but packed with plenty of information in a long format. You can:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Find </span><a href="https://tothetrains.uk/tags/railway-rover-podcast/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">all episodes on </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">tothetrains.uk</span></i></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Listen on </span><a href="https://open.spotify.com/show/6AXt5io5xeNhllevcap9Uo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Spotify</span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Listen on </span><a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/railway-rover/id1583915799" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Apple Podcasts</span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Listen on </span><a href="https://www.google.com/podcasts?feed=aHR0cHM6Ly9mZWVkcy5yZWRjaXJjbGUuY29tL2JkMGJjMjkzLTE2NjktNGVlOS1hNWM2LWMzYzdjMWUxNWJkNg%3D%3D" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Google Podcasts</span></a></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You can also listen on all other major podcast listening platforms. Just search for "Railway Rover" to get started.</span></p>
<h4>Ambroise from TrainFan World</h4>
<ul>
<li>TrainFan World on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCcFN6cQI6JmyH3b1fBUbbEw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">YouTube</a></li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The LNER Class 801 &quot;Azuma&quot;</title>
        <author>
            <name>Seb J.</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tothetrains.uk/lner-class-801-azuma-overview/"/>
        <id>https://tothetrains.uk/lner-class-801-azuma-overview/</id>

        <updated>2023-07-31T20:27:11+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/001-01-ext-2.jpg" alt="The LNER Class 801 &quot;Azuma&quot; at Peterborough" />
                    <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Class 801 electric multiple units are operated by London North Eastern Railway under the Azuma brand, and were brought into service in 2019 under the Intercity Express Programme.</span></p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/001-01-ext-2.jpg" alt="The LNER Class 801 &quot;Azuma&quot; at Peterborough" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Class 801 electric multiple units are operated by London North Eastern Railway under the Azuma brand, and were brought into service in 2019 under the Intercity Express Programme.</span></p>

<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/wVyMPsV2jQY" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<hr>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These units were introduced as part of the Department for Transport’s aforementioned Intercity Express Programme, which saw Hitachi’s AT300 trains succeed the ageing InterCity 125 and InterCity 225 fleets on the East Coast Main Line and Great Western Main Line.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--wide"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/001-01-ext.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/responsive/001-01-ext-xs.jpg 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/responsive/001-01-ext-sm.jpg 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/responsive/001-01-ext-md.jpg 768w"  alt="Class 801 &quot;Azuma&quot; at Peterborough" width="4032" height="3024"></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">They were initially being manufactured for both London North Eastern Railway and Great Western Railway, however, in 2016, GWR announced they would update their order to Class 800/3 units for bi-modal operation. This was due to delays in the electrification of the Great Western Main Line, and the Class 801s only being fitted with a single diesel engine for emergency use only.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">LNER is operating twelve 5-car /1 units and a further thirty 9-car /2 units. These first entered service with doubled-up /1s on the 16th of September in 2019, and later that year, the 9-car units were introduced on the 18th of November. Alongside the Class 801s, LNER also operates 23 Class 800 BMUs.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--left"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/001-02-seating.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/responsive/001-02-seating-xs.jpg 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/responsive/001-02-seating-sm.jpg 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/responsive/001-02-seating-md.jpg 768w"  alt="Standard Class 2+2 seating arrangement in an airline-style layout" width="1920" height="1080"></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In standard class, there is a 2+2 seating configuration, with a variety of single and table seats in each coach. On the backs of single seats are relatively compact fold-down tables, and there are also foldable armrests. Plenty of space to store luggage can be found at the ends of each coach, with more space both under and above your seat. Electronic seat reservation is also utilised, with displays above each seat. Power sockets can be found between each pair of seats for laptops and phones, and where available, there is also food and drink service which is delivered directly to your seat. There are wheelchair spaces and accessible toilets onboard, as well, should you need them.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">First Class offers a variety of enhancements, including access to LNER first class lounges, though the value of these upgrades is subjective.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right"><img loading="lazy"  style="font-size: 18.4px; outline: 3px solid rgba(var(--primary-color-rgb), 0.55)  !important;" src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/001-03-first-2.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/responsive/001-03-first-2-xs.jpg 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/responsive/001-03-first-2-sm.jpg 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/responsive/001-03-first-2-md.jpg 768w"  alt="The 2+1 seating arrangement in LNER First Class on the Class 801" width="1920" height="1080"></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Following the rollout of the Class 800 BMUs and the Class 801 EMUs, further orders for AT300 units have been placed by various train operating companies in the UK, although these are not under the Intercity Express Programme. Great Western Railway have since ordered several additional units for their IET fleet, and Hull Trains are now operating Class 802 Paragon units. TransPennine Express have also taken interest in the Class 802s, and these are now in service under the ‘Nova’ fleet overhaul. Furthermore, East Midlands Railway and Avanti West Coast both announced orders for various AT300 trains in 2019.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/001-04-paragon.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 61.3125em) 50vw, 100vw" srcset="https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/responsive/001-04-paragon-xs.jpg 300w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/responsive/001-04-paragon-sm.jpg 480w ,https://tothetrains.uk/media/posts/7/responsive/001-04-paragon-md.jpg 768w"  alt="Hull Trains Class 802 Paragon at London King's Cross" width="1579" height="1028">
<figcaption >A Class 802 "Paragon" sat in London King's Cross</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And if that wasn’t enough for you, the recently-unveiled budget-operator Lumo will be operating five 5-car Class 803s for its open access service beginning October 2021. As yet another subsidiary of FirstGroup, this TOC will be running two trains per day in either direction to offer a budget service from London to Edinburgh. It’s certainly an interesting strategy, and one that can be likened to many budget airlines, but with limited capacity, I’m holding my breath. However, if Lumo does turn out to be a relative success, we might see them expanding to the West Coast Main Line, for example.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The IETs are subject to an immense volume of criticism from rail enthusiasts, and the conversation comparing IETs to their predecessors amasses plenty of debate. With the concern surrounding cracks discovered in Hitachi trains aside, the IETs do just what they were brought into do. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Most of the time.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Railway Rover: A Bit About Branch Lines</title>
        <author>
            <name>Seb J.</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tothetrains.uk/railway-rover-a-bit-about-branch-lines/"/>
        <id>https://tothetrains.uk/railway-rover-a-bit-about-branch-lines/</id>
            <category term="Railway Rover"/>

        <updated>2022-01-30T21:59:46+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    For the first episode of Railway Rover we’re joined by Sean from WMTrainspotting today to discuss a bit about Britain’s various branch lines and regional routes. We take a look at the defining characteristics of these smaller lines, as well as the upgrades, particularly relevant&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For the first episode of <a href="https://tothetrains.uk/tags/railway-rover-podcast/">Railway Rover</a> we’re joined by Sean from WMTrainspotting today to discuss a bit about Britain’s various branch lines and regional routes. We take a look at the defining characteristics of these smaller lines, as well as the upgrades, particularly relevant to the rolling stock, that these lines have seen recently. Britain’s branch lines serve as the backbone for many small communities, and we also delve into the viability of operating regional services and what the re-nationalisation of the railway means for them.</span></p>
<h4>Watch on YouTube</h4>
<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/wE56vHc35jA" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<h4>Railway Rover</h4>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Railway Rover is your all line rover ticket to the latest in the rail industry. It's a podcast covering everything from rolling stock to routes, laid-back and conversational by design, but packed with plenty of information in a long format. You can:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Find </span><a href="https://tothetrains.uk/tags/railway-rover-podcast/" target="null">all episodes on <em>tothetrains.uk</em></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Listen on </span><a href="https://open.spotify.com/show/6AXt5io5xeNhllevcap9Uo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Spotify</span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Listen on </span><a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/railway-rover/id1583915799" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Apple Podcasts</span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Listen on </span><a href="https://www.google.com/podcasts?feed=aHR0cHM6Ly9mZWVkcy5yZWRjaXJjbGUuY29tL2JkMGJjMjkzLTE2NjktNGVlOS1hNWM2LWMzYzdjMWUxNWJkNg%3D%3D" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Google Podcasts</span></a></li>
</ul>
<h4>WMTrainspotting</h4>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">WMTrainspotting on </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://youtube.com/wmtrainspotting" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">YouTube</a></span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1">WMTrainspotting on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/redirect?event=video_description&amp;redir_token=QUFFLUhqbkVFX0otMW5sdFppbzE1bzAtcW1peFpJMTNwd3xBQ3Jtc0tucVZsYVNqTG5CVmhoWmpKaWk1ZlhmajVScjhyUmh6R1hxZk5lZjYxN0NPNWtaOXVRejRQYzVRWjRKVlV3UUVyNFlhT01icXJ1TlJZTkZSZlFkV1VGemZMdjc5dW56WEF4akZHTEkxSDFCOVI3WUZPVQ&amp;q=https%3A%2F%2Ftwitter.com%2Fwmtrainspotting" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Twitter</a></li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Railway Rover: Introduction</title>
        <author>
            <name>Seb J.</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tothetrains.uk/railway-rover-introduction/"/>
        <id>https://tothetrains.uk/railway-rover-introduction/</id>
            <category term="Railway Rover"/>

        <updated>2022-01-30T21:59:56+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Introducing Railway Rover, your all line rover ticket to the latest in the rail industry. Be sure to check back in a few weeks for the first episode from Seb from To The Trains and a special guest from the community. They'll be discussing everything&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Introducing <a href="https://tothetrains.uk/tags/railway-rover-podcast/">Railway Rover</a>, your all line rover ticket to the latest in the rail industry. Be sure to check back in a few weeks for the first episode from Seb from To The Trains and a special guest from the community. They'll be discussing everything from rolling stock to the routes of the UK's various train operating companies.</p>
<h4>Watch on YouTube</h4>
<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/ZSDWtSqW9JU" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<h4>Railway Rover</h4>
<p>Railway Rover is your all line rover ticket to the latest in the rail industry. It's a podcast covering everything from rolling stock to routes, laid-back and conversational by design, but packed with plenty of information in a long format. You can:</p>
<ul>
<li>Find <a href="https://tothetrains.uk/tags/railway-rover-podcast/">all episodes on <em>tothetrains.uk</em></a></li>
<li>Listen on <a href="https://open.spotify.com/show/6AXt5io5xeNhllevcap9Uo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Spotify</a></li>
<li>Listen on <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/railway-rover/id1583915799" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Apple Podcasts</a></li>
<li>Listen on <a href="https://www.google.com/podcasts?feed=aHR0cHM6Ly9mZWVkcy5yZWRjaXJjbGUuY29tL2JkMGJjMjkzLTE2NjktNGVlOS1hNWM2LWMzYzdjMWUxNWJkNg%3D%3D" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Google Podcasts</a></li>
</ul>
<p>You can also listen on all other major podcast listening platforms. Just search for "Railway Rover" to get started.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
